Guide to the Cornell-Bouck family papers, [ca. 1770-1900]
Cornell-Bouck family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell-Bouck family papers, [ca. 1770-1900]
8502
Cornell family.
2 cubic feet.
Correspondence, newspapers, printed material, memorabilia, legal documents, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers from the family of Alonzo Cornell and his son, Charles Ezra and daughter-in-law, Katherine Bouck.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers from the family of Alonzo Cornell and his son, Charles Ezra and daughter-in-law, Katherine Bouck.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell family.; Bouck family.; Bouck family.; Cornell family.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Alonzo B. Cornell Materials
Subseries Ia. Incoming Correspondence
Subseries Ib. Outgoing Correspondence
Subseries Ic. Miscellaneous Materials
Series II. Ezra Cornell Materials
Subseries IIa. Incoming Correspondence
Subseries IIb. Outgoing Correspondence
Subseries IIc. Miscellaneous Materials
Series III. Cornell Family Documents and Materials
Subseries IIIa. Charles Ezra Cornell
Subseries IIIb. Miscellaneous Materials
Series IV. Bouck Family Materials
Subseries IVa. William C. Bouck
Subseries IVb. Miscellaneous Materials
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Alonzo Cornell Materials (Box 1)
  - Subseries Ia. Incoming Correspondence
    - Letters from Ezra Cornell, 1845-1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Ezra Cornell, 1848-1849 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Ezra Cornell, 1853-1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Ezra Cornell, 1862-1872 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1848-1849 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes letters from H. Bronson and Margaret
    - Correspondence, 1850-1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes letters from Otis E. Wood, A. Oakey Hall, DH Craig, and Colonel John C. Fremont
    - Correspondence, 1864-1866 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes letters from G. Schuyler, D. Boardman, Thomas Faile Jr., HB Lord, O. Wood, WC Curran, and Alfred Wells
    - Correspondence, 1867-1869 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes letters from John Meredith Read, Friedrich Schuk, Judge Folger, J. Selkreg, G. Schuyler, D. Boardman, Thomas Strong, GC Caldwell, Wesley Hooker, and Edward Underhill
    - Correspondence, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Letter from Horace Greeley
    - Correspondence, 1882-1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes letters from William Bogardt and James Blaine,
    - Correspondence, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes letters from WW Astor, JB Foraker, Stewart Woodford, Albert Shaw, William Bogardt, and B. Lucy
    - Correspondence, 1893-1897 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes letters from Crane, Elijah Coffue, and Mayor of NY
    - Correspondence, 1899-1912 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes letters from the President's secretary, Mayor of NY, Charles Hughes, and Jacob Gould Schurman,
    - Republican Party letters and letterheads, 1859-1878 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters and notes from Civil War soldiers, 1861-1868 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters regarding New York State politics, 1856-1862 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes letters from D. Boardman, O. Sawyer, Horace Greeley, Jas. Terwilliger, T. Platt, Charles Cook, and William S. Lincoln
    - Political correspondence, 1860-1866 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes letters from Jas. Terwilliger
    - Political correspondence, 1867-1872 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes letters from Oliver Hurd, DS Bennett, OW Chapman, JS Thurston, George Otis, JH Selkreg, GW Schuyler, R. Sidney, Charles K. Graham, and several others
    - Letter from Grover Cleveland, December, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Roscoe Conkling, 1866-1889 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters from President-Elect Harrison, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Discusses possible appointment of Alonzo Cornell to his cabinet
    - Letters from GW Hotchkiss, 1865-1868 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Thomas C. Platt, 1864-1865 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letter from CA Scroggs, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Describes living with Abraham Lincoln and his impressions
    - Letters from Andrew Dickson White, 1871, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters regarding early days of the telegraph, 1848-1882 (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
      Includes some outgoing correspondence
    - Letter from Elijah Cornell to Alonzo, with Elijah's will, 1857,1830 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Subseries Ib. Outgoing Correspondence
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1844-1846 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Outgoing letters, mainly to family members, 1845-1847 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1852-1853 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1854-1856 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1857-1859 (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1861-1863 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1864-1865 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
      Includes letter about building the library
    - Letters to Mary Ann and Ezra Cornell, 1866-1869 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Outgoing letters, 1865 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Includes letters to Gov. Fenton, Charles Cornell, and the bank
    - Letter to Governor Roosevelt, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Subseries Ic. Miscellaneous Documents
    - "Life of Ezra Cornell", by Alonzo Cornell, original manuscript (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "Recognition by the United States of Foreign Powers", by Alonzo Cornell (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Handwritten biography of Alonzo Cornell (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Alonzo's telegraph abbreviation notebook with clippings, 1846 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Compositions, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Fall Creek deed, sketches, and maps, 1853 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Alonzo Cornell references, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Alonzo Cornell and Lucius Colby contract, 1860 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Railroad tickets, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Petition from Binghamton to State Senate, regarding stockholders and offices, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Bank checks, 1871-1874 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Promissory notes, Alonzo and Ezra Cornell, 1874-1884 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Ledgers, 1881-1889 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Alonzo Cornell and Virgil Blauchard contract, and contract with TD Wilcox, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Letters from AD White to Mrs Alonzo Cornell, 1903-1905 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Letters from Jacob Gould Schurman to Mrs. Alonzo Cornell, 1904-1907 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Silver name plaque from casket, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Clippings and articles collected in scrapbook by Alonzo Cornell (Box 10)
    - Ledger book (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Series II. Ezra Cornell Materials
  - Subseries IIa. Incoming Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1862-1873 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes letters from Jay Gould, Mary Ann Cornell, Goldwin Smith, Stewart Woodford, James Law, and William Russell
    - Letters regarding railroads, 1870s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters from GF Lewis, land warrant broker, 1866-1872 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters from John Mcgraw, 1870-1874 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Hiram Sibley, 1870-1872 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Henry Sage to Ezra Cornell, 1871-1873 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Letters from AD White, regarding the purchase of the cast collection, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries IIb. Outgoing Correspondence
    - Typescripts, with edits and notes, and photostats of letters from Ezra Cornell to his wife Mary Ann Cornell (Box 11)
    - Old folders with descriptions of letters from Ezra to Alonzo and Mary Ann (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1866, 1874 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Mary Ann, 1843-1845 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letters to Mary Ann, 1852-1855 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Letters to Mary Ann, 1856-1871 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
      Includes letter from March, 1861 describing Mr. and Mrs. Lincoln, in folder 11
    - Letters to Mary Ann, 1871-1872 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letters to Horace Greeley regarding St. Croix land grant (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Subseries IIc. Miscellaneous Materials
    - Letter to Governor from OEW, transcribed by EEC (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Typed story of Cornell and the Telegraph (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Page from the Cipher book, 1822 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Souvenir coin given to Ezra by the mayor of New York City on the opening of the Erie Canal. In a wooden box made from wood shipped on the first boat to go through the canals, 1826 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Signed petition from Binghamton to Ezra, 1867 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Cornell versus Woodward documents, 1870s (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Appeal book for the settlement of Ezra Cornell's estate, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Hand-written biography of Ezra Cornell, written on the back of 1892 Ithaca Building Co. printouts, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series III. Cornell Family Documents and Materials
  - Subseries IIIa. Charles Ezra Cornell
    - Records at Columbia University, graduates, 1877-1878 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Letter from Charles to Frank Cornell, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Letters and documents to Charles regarding New York State agriculture, 1895, 1839 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Incoming correspondence and papers, 1876. 1895-1909 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Includes letters from Alonzo Cornell and Orrin Wood
    - Incoming correspondence, 1910-1939 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Includes letters from Cuthbert Pound, Charles Hughes, and Herbert Lehman
    - Letters from George and Inez Fields, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Theodore Roosevelt autograph, to Charles (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Map of Africa from Charles's room (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - State of New York Attorney and Counsellor certificate, 1880 (Folder 1)
    - Union University Albany Law School bachelor diploma, 1880 (Folder 1)
    - Columbia bachelor diploma (Folder 1)
    - Notary Public certificate, 1882-1884 (Folder 1)
  - Subseries IIIb. Miscellaneous materials
    - Signatures (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Copies of engraving of Alonzo Cornell (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Cornell stationary (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 10 cent fractional currency (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Marriage service, William B. Cornell and Emily (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Wedding invitations (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Inventory books (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Two daily diaries, one from Charles Cornell, one unknown (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Ledgers (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Bible (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Rocks from Pompeii, sand from where St. Peter was martyred, bullet from Saratoga battlefield, and buttons from a US Uniform (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Bank pouch and receipts (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Cornell related clippings and articles (Box 9, Folder 18-20)
    - Timothy Murphy documents, 1780s-1800s (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Elijah Cornell indenture, 1791 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Letter from Elijah Cornell to his wife, 1810 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1818-1940 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Lottery tickets, 1826, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - DR Wood letter to Mary Ann Cornell, 1845 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Letter to Edwin Cornell, 1846 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Letter to "father", unknown sender, 1848 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Cornell Bills, Notes, etc., 1850-1858 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Cornell related reports and pamphlets, 1858-1954 (Box 9, Folder 9-11)
    - Cayuga Lake operatim of boats, passenger fares etc., 1861-1863 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Real Estate inventory (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Funeral program for U.S. Grant (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Deeds and mortgages, James Covert, Katherine and Charles Cornell, 1877-1907 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Governor's message, 1881-1882 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Letter to Franklin Cornell from Thomas Rooker, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Thanksgiving Day Proclamation, 1882 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - "History of the Class of Seventy Nine of Columbia College", written by the historian, 1882-1883 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Photograph of clocks possibly made by Ithaca Calendar Clock Co, and article about Alonzo Cornell clock story, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Calling cards of prominent persons, late 1800s (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Note regarding the commission of the Ezra Cornell portrait, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Highway route certification, Town of Fulton, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Letter to Mary E Cornell, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - William Bouck Cornell letter, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Letter from the White House to William B, Cornell, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - William B. Cornell biography information, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - William B. Cornell stock information from Yervan Maxudian, 1915-1921 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Inventory of books, including correspondence with book dealers, post-1940 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Letters to Cornell University regarding gift of William B. Cornell, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Katherine B. Cornell shares, application for "Daughters of the Revolution", 1918 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Cornell genealogy (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Benjamin Wood genealogy, and miscellaneous genealogies (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Photograph of the house on the corner of Seneca and Tioga street, Ithaca, where Ezra Cornell died. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Velvet pin cushion given by William B. Cornell to his mother, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Invitations to Boucks and Cornells (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - William B. Cornell American Society of Mechanical Engineers member certificate, 1922 (Folder 2)
    - William B. Cornell The University of the State of New York license to practice engineering, 1924 (Folder 2)
    - William B. Cornell renewal certificate, 1925 (Folder 2)
    - William B. Cornell Institute of Management certificate, 1928 (Folder 2)
- Series IV. Bouck Family Materials
  - Subseries IVa. William C. Bouck
    - Legal receipts (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Schoharie patents, leases, 1786-1833 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Certification of election to NY State Senate, 1802 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous legal documents, 1805-1855 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
    - Certificates of appointments as sheriff, assemblyman, and military positions, 1812-1840 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Letters to WC Bouck, 1812-1819 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Notes and receipts, 1812-1866 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Agreement between Peter Hoes and WC Bouck, 1813 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Deeds, 1814-1850 (Box 8, Folder 9-11)
    - Letters regarding bank practices, from D. Beckman, 1820 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Letters to WC Bouck, 1838-1857 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
    - Letter from John Titus, 1845 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Insurance information, 1846 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Letters regarding the California gold rush, 1849-1850 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Treasury documents and correspondence (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Bouck article in Schoharie Newspaper, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Part of the card case of William Bouck's wife (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Perpetual calendar, William Bouck (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Bouck photo (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Epaulettes from WC Bouck's jacket (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Subseries IVb. Miscellaneous Materials
    - Map of Schoharie Valley showing route traversed by Colonel Sir John Johnson in 1780 raid (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Camp Wahalla Booklet (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Bouck clippings (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Signature of William Pauck, scripture leaves, 1740 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Infantry appointments for Christyan Bauck, Joseph Bouck, 1793, 1829 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Agreement on sale of a slave, 1797 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Certification of V. Danforth as Physician and Surgeon, 1836 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Letter from Charles Bouck to father, 1843 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Transcript of the Account of William Bouck, 1849 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Charles Bouck, made member of the town war committee, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Statement on condition of banks, 1843 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Letter from Francis Bouck to Mrs. Charles Bouck, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Bouck family history, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Genealogy charts (Folder 2)